<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Great news from Poland: being an impartial account of the election of a new King, in the room of Anthony, by the grace of God lately deceased</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85609</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1729</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230061</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895894</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895894</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153448</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85609)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153448)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2365:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Great news from Poland: being an impartial account of the election of a new King, in the room of Anthony, by the grace of God lately deceased</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the assigns of F. S.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A Tory satire on Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of Shaftesbury.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, 1621-1683 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:153448:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Great News from Poland:</hi> BEING An Impartial Account of the Election OF A New KING, In the Room of ANTHONY, By the Grace of GOD lately Deceaſed.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Polonians</hi> had no ſooner receiv'd the ſurprizing News of the departure of their late King, but they pay'd the Tears which were due to His Memory, wip'd their eyes, blew their Noſes, and conſider'd of a perſon fit to ſucceed. The Candidates who appear'd were numerous; Prince <hi>Prettyman Perkinoski</hi> appear'd in the Van, but they ſoon voted him <hi>non compos mentis:</hi> becauſe, though he was ſatisfied himſelf <hi>he was unlawfully begotten,</hi> yet he ply'd next Oars for an <hi>Hereditary Crown. Capellanoff le grand</hi> made a conſiderable Intereſt in the Dyet, out he was thrown out too, becauſe, whil'ſt but a <hi>Vice-Roy,</hi> he had miſs-imploy'd and imbez'l'd the Revenues that came near his hands; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, he had taken upon him the imploy of being <hi>the Mouth of the People of England,</hi> and <hi>their Clark too,</hi> to draw up their <hi>unmannerly Petitions. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes Sheffieldiſlaus</hi> acquainted the Dyet, that as ſoon as he was dreſs'd, he would viſit them, to aſſure them, that he was not ſo ſupercilious as to deſpiſe the Government of <hi>Poland;</hi> And that, being diſappointed of the <hi>Firſt</hi> he aſpir'd to, he was reſolv'd to take the <hi>Next</hi> was proffer'd him. [But you are to underſtand by the way, that the Nobility of <hi>Poland</hi> are very familiar with their King; and having ſmoak'd the haughtineſs of this Spark's heart, his buſineſs was diſpatch'd.]</p>
            <p>To reckon up all the Pretenders would be too tedious; therefore, in ſhort, the choice fell upon <hi>Arthur</hi> E. of <hi>A—y,</hi> adjudg'd by the moſt prudent part of the Dyet the fitteſt Perſon to ſucceed <hi>Anthony;</hi> and that, for his Religion, his Principles of Honour and Honeſty, his Natural Averſion to a Lineal Deſcent, for proof of his Religion, there needed no more, than that there have been entertain'd <hi>Men of all perſwaſions</hi> at this <hi>King</hi> Arthur<hi>'s Round-Table,</hi> (for we muſt no longer call him plain <hi>Arthur.</hi>) Such a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per as this is chiefly requiſite in a <hi>Poliſh King:</hi> It being ſaid of <hi>Poland, That he that has loſt his Religion, may eaſily find it there.</hi> There ſhalt thou glut thy ſelf, O King <hi>Arthur!</hi> Thou admired Patron of Toleration; There you may pay the reſpects you owe to the <hi>Romanists,</hi> to the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> to the <hi>Calvinists,</hi> to the <hi>Arrians, Anabaptiſts, Anti-Trinitarians, &amp;c.</hi> and thy Royal Conſort Queen <hi>Beſs,</hi> may, to her hearts deſire, ſit in ſtate in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle every day.</p>
            <p>His Principles of Honour and Honeſty appeared by his under-hand dealings with <hi>Toney</hi> of curſed memory; His averſion to the Succeſſion was ſuch, that the greateſt ties of gratitude could not reconcile him to it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:153448:2"/>
            <p>Thus did King <hi>Arthur</hi> carry it from all the Pretenders; but what teem'd moſt of his ſide, was, his <hi>Old Age,</hi> and <hi>Decrepidneſs;</hi> for the Electors of <hi>Poland</hi> love to ſhift their Kings as faſt as they can; and long as much for election of a <hi>King,</hi> as any bawling <hi>Forty-ſhilling-Free-holder</hi> does in <hi>England</hi> for a new <hi>Knight of the Shire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majeſty (we hear) has made ſome alterations of the great Officers of State, as well as thoſe about his gouty Perſon: having reſolv'd to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer none but ſuch as merit his gracious Favour, whoſe Names are as follow:
<list>
                  <item>Boreaski Whad-d'ye-call-himski, <hi>Lord High-Chancellor of</hi> Poland.</item>
                  <item>Microcoſmus Audbryjus, <hi>Generaliſſimo of his Forces, upon condition he do greater Martial Feats than thoſe of</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</item>
                  <item>* <hi>Note, That it is thought King</hi> Arthur <hi>will be his own <hi>Privy-Seal.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Humpbackgundi Eſcrickski, <hi>Archbiſhop of</hi> Cracovia, <hi>Lord Almoner, and Dean of the (happel, for cheapneſs-ſake: having a way of re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>renching the</hi> Sacrament, <hi>by administring with</hi> Lambs-wool.</item>
                  <item>Capellanoff le grand, <hi>Lord High-Treaſurer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Monſ. Acutus Bloomsburienſis, <hi>Embaſſador Extraordinary upon all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts: having the faculty of betraying the ſecrets of any Embaſsy to the Dyet.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lord Chamberlain continued.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Seignior Tho. Strongarmski, <hi>By her Majeſties interceſſion, firſt Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Bed-Chamber: provided he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more converſe with</hi> Botelia.</item>
                  <item>Bloodowndsby Howardski, <hi>Grooms of the Bed-Chamber, in caſe they tell every thing they hear.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Moroſo Progero, <hi>Grooms of the Bed-Chamber, in caſe they tell every thing they hear.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Finicalki Babercelaus, <hi>Eſquires of the Body.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Pimpanello Forbeſius, <hi>Groom of the Stool, and Policy-reader to them that cannot read about</hi> Court.</item>
                  <item>Gilbertus Groaningboardellus, <hi>Confeſsor to her Majeſty, provided they will not gueld him when he goes over.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Monſieur Papillionski, <hi>Sheriffs of</hi> Cracovia, <hi>without any oppoſition.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Monſieur Duboienski, <hi>Sheriffs of</hi> Cracovia, <hi>without any oppoſition.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Her Majeſty has only as yet made choice (being wholly devoted to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) of Her Chaplains, and is now only taken up in repenting (if poſſible) the God-nepping Act in <hi>Poland:</hi> being in Her Royal Opinion as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Presbytery as the <hi>35th.</hi> of Her Name in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>GOD Save the QUEEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for the Aſſigns of <hi>F. S.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
